## **Avi Mitra**

IMPROVING REVENUE, CREATING OPERATIONAL EXCELLENCE THROUGH NEXT GENERATION TECHNOLOGY AND DIGITAL ECOSYSTEM LEADERSHIP



8 April Dr, Dayton, NJ 08810 • (732) 824-2709 • avimitra@gmail.com • LinkedIn

## **Executive Summary**

Highly accomplished Senior IT Executive noted for positively transforming IT organizations towards greater business outcomes. More than two decades of proven success across four continents consistently enhancing internal and external customer experience. collaborative leader and trusted business partner who recognizes the "mindset" and gets people to think differently through change management, improves organizational effectiveness through leadership that alians the business and technology realize innovation, operational productivity, effectiveness and sustain strategic flexibility, while creating a competitive advantage for the organization.

## Expertise

- Technology Operations & Transformation
- Service Management & Excellence
- Cloud Strategy
- Digital Transformation
- Banking Technology Operations Transformation
- Product Offering Strategy & Lifecycle Management
- Change Management
- Large Global Vendor Management
- Global Resource Management

## Achievements

- Growing the Business Through Transformational Technology: Played a pivotal role in growing Kenya Commercial Bank's revenue. Provided business and technology thought leadership in architecting a mobile application that increased the market share of the Bank extensively within a year from 2 million to 12 million customers, Co-Owned business strategy & Lead digital transformation and change management. My leadership had led to increased market share while taking it to the top position in digital financial leadership in the region as recognized in a leading global business magazine in the region within 2 years. Created a portfolio of Private and Public cloud technology environment and utilized DevOps culture towards faster Go-To market.
- Creating Superior IT Operations: Established 99.99% stabilized datacenter environment in less than 3 months for a large insurance Client based in Connecticut, USA. This had resulted in a winning deal for my current Employer, one of the largest in 2017.
  - Strengthened the IT organizational structure to effectively meet the current and future needs of Kenya Commercial Bank, both regionally and internationally. Quickly stabilized its technology environment, while improving business availability from 94% to 99.99% within the first 8 months. Brought revenue leakages to minimum, Elevated Customer Experience scores from 67% to 82% within the first two years. Established company-wide service management culture effectively to improve operational excellence. Ensured IT system operation adheres to applicable laws and regulations, including ownership of IT risk management and security strategy.
- Driving and Supporting Change on a Global Scale: Drove development and implementation of strategic initiatives within the specific IT discipline for the company. Involved senior executives and the Board in the development and understanding of the plans and initiatives and led the IT team in the execution of those plans. Successfully transformed core banking application for Kenya Commercial Bank from legacy Temenos T24-vR8 to T24-vR14 bringing the Bank to the forefront of banking technologies and technology operational processes and standards.
  - Planned and guided JPMorgan Chase's Global Service Center move to India. Teamed with CTOs to transition areas of Private Banking, Investment Banking and Card Services. Concurrently supported multiple Data Centers in global locations to reduce operational cost by ~40%.
- Leading High-Performance Teams: Developed global teams with as many as 140 direct at Kenya Commercial Bank and 350 indirect reports at IBM from ground up, while constantly maturing them toward service excellence. Promoted a culture that is user focused with outstanding customer experience, high performance and accountability. Provided effective leadership, management of teams, prioritizing goals and objectives to ensure effectiveness towards the company's objectives.

### **Education**

# Work Experience

### Cognizant Technologies, Bridgewater, NJ, USA 2016 – Present

Cognizant Technologies is a global leader in business and technology services, helping its clients bring the future of work to life – today.

#### SENIOR DIRECTOR, LARGE INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAMS

**Recruited to help the firm capture a large outsourcing deal with a US-based Insurance provider.** Serve as a Client Program Director to ensure the successful execution of large Infrastructure projects with a yearly TCV of >\$100M. Plan and direct program aspects, including initiation, transition, transformation and delivery to operations.

**Isolating Pain Points to Improve the Customer Experience:** Positioned at a high-value potential client to eliminate the primary causes of severe technology operational failures and poor delivery, while providing Cognizant with a distinct advantage over competing vendors.

Identified and addressed long-standing client performance issues related to business and technology alignment, poor internal communications, immature technology organizations, legacy technologies and lack of synergies.

**Driving Growth Globally:** Played a pivotal role in positioning Cognizant in the forefront among other incumbents, while serving as a trusted advisor and strategic partner to clients with a global reach and agenda. Led design and delivery of multinational/multipartner projects, while serving as the key technical contributor for project management methodology and tools.

**Responsible for Offering Strategy & Life Cycle Management:** Create offering strategy, new offerings, define roadmap for life cycle management for new & existing offerings. Work with Client Senior & Executive leadership, internal and external cross-functional & market research teams to create relevant portfolio of offerings.

### Kenya Commercial Bank (KCB), Nairobi, Kenya

2014 - 2016

Kenya Commercial Bank is a financial services provider headquartered in Nairobi, Kenya.

#### CHIEF INFORMATION OFFICER, MEMBER OF EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE

Recruited to halt revenue losses precipitated by technology operational issues, legacy core banking software and almost nonexistent digital initiative. Drove continuing improvement in IT services and infrastructure supporting the bank's operations in Kenya, Rwanda, Uganda, South Sudan, Tanzania, Ethiopia and Burundi.

Provided leadership in planning, architecting, implementing and managing the Bank's core and noncore technology infrastructure. Held authority for enterprise architecture, Information Security, Risk Management and Operations. Drove continuing improvement in data centers, WAN/LAN telecommunications, converged/distributed systems, end-user technology and IT asset management.

**Providing Superior Strategic Planning:** Set and championed the overall strategic direction of the IT Organization at Executive Committee and Board level. Implemented the IT aspects of the strategic plan and mission. Foster innovative IT initiatives and developed compelling business cases for their implementation.

**Identifying and Eliminating Performance Issues:** Addressed issues related to illegal software usage, legacy infrastructure, lack of skills, poor IT investments, data center reliability, and poor communications between IT and the Business. Established formal communications with the Executive Committee and the Board of Directors, upgraded core banking software, improved talent at the individual and team level, and elevated system reliability to 99.99%. Consolidated data centers to reduce operational costs by 37% in 2015 and then 18% in 2016.

**Delivering Measurable Improvement:** Grew percentage of total revenue of the Group through digital channels from 15% to 33%. Improved mobile revenue by 30% in 2015 and 33% in 2016, while earning recognition for the best mobile financial services tool in East Africa in 2015.

### MSCI (Morgan Stanley Capital International) Pvt. Ltd., Mumbai, India

2011 - 2014

MSCI is a US-based provider of equity, fixed income, and hedge fund stock market indexes, and equity portfolio analysis tools.

### **VICE PRESIDENT, GLOBAL ASSURANCE (GSA)**

**Brought on to improve IT response to business requirements and better support key business stakeholders.** Provided global leadership over Infrastructure and Application Support to MCSI Businesses, particularly the research and statistical units, the company's highest revenue earner.

Established, owned and directed service delivery organization in India. Drove migration of large support projects to India. Actively coprogram managed Data Center transformation projects, successfully executed in North America and Europe.

Planned and directed the efforts of global teams in Service Desk, Wintel Linux/Storage/Backup that delivered and assure 100% availability of services across the company. Planned and managed projects that made a substantial positive impact on the Company's top clients.

**Partnering with the Business to Improve Performance.** Developed strong relations with the global heads of the MSCI businesses by actively providing inputs in their strategies. Developed and implemented Continual Service Improvement projects to improve turn-around time and productivity.

**Building High-Performance Teams:** Dramatically improved synergies between and within the multiple teams under the CIO organization. Created a highly trained team that eliminated silos, implemented process and discipline, and dramatically strengthened the business support model.

# Work Experience

### IBM India Pvt. Ltd., Bangalore, India

2008 - 2011

IBM India Private Limited is the Indian subsidiary of IBM with facilities in 14 of India's largest cities.

### **DELIVERY PROJECT EXECUTIVE (DPE), ITD - GLOBAL DELIVERY**

Brought on to direct end-to-end technology service delivery for global MNCs and public sectors for large clients in onshore-offshore model. Took the lead in account planning and strategy, SLA development and compliance, account budgeting, project management, disaster recovery, and business and continuity planning, as well as in incident and change management.

**Setting the Foundation for Continuing Improvement:** Identified areas of potential revenue growth and cost reduction. Partnered with Business Development/Engagement Teams to generate incremental revenues.

### Navisite India Pvt. Ltd., New Delhi, India

2007 - 2008

Navisite is a provider of hosting, application management and managed cloud services for enterprises.

### **DIRECTOR, SERVICE DELIVERY (INFRASTRUCTURE)**

Hired to drive continuing improvement in the quality and delivery of all remote infrastructure management services emanating out of India and supporting all the lines of business. Built and managed on-site/off-site and direct teams with as many as # professionals. Responsibly managed budgets as large as \$3M.

**Raising the Performance Bar:** Developed and implemented processes and procedures that improved availability and performance, decreased system faults, lowered costs, and delivered higher levels of client satisfaction. Helped Navisite to extend support contract with one of its largest Clients that had wanted to terminate due to poor delivery.

**Driving Change:** Partnered with US and UK counterparts to transition infrastructure management activities into a remote model. Comanaged implementation of BladeLogic technology at multiple Data Centers.

## AXA Group Solutions, Bangalore, India

2006 - 2007

AXA Group Solutions is an IT solutions company delivering services to the Group AXA and to its banking and insurance companies.

### **OFFSHORE RELATIONSHIP MANAGER**

**Brought on to establish, implement and operate robust offshore operations in India for AXA group of companies** (AXA-US, AXA-UK) and AXA Group Solutions. Planned and managed the transitioning, maintenance and support of all mission critical applications. Worked in close collaboration with US and UK counterparts to complete a \$54M initiative on time and on budget.

Setting the Foundation for Superior Service Delivery: Assisted in establishing Centers of Excellence as per global SDLC practices. Formalized internal process to ramp-up expertise of resources in the offshore centers. Migrated 36 application development/maintenance projects from the US and UK. Successfully established a Global Shared Services for Technology Testing Center of Excellence for AXA Business Services within the first year.

### JPMorgan Chase & Co., New York City, NY

1996 - 2006

JPMorgan Chase is a leading global financial services firm and one of the largest banking institutions in the US.

### SENIOR CAPACITY AND PERFORMANCE MANAGER. STRUCTURED TECHNOLOGY AND OPERATIONS, 2005 - 2006

Converted from a consultant to a full-time manager and moved to the company's Global Service Center. Teamed with CTOs to transition areas of Private Banking, Investment Banking and Card Services in shared services model to India. Determined end of life for apps and infrastructure supported by GSC, as well as network bandwidth and application performance necessary to support demand from lines of business utilizing GSC.

**Improving Performance Management:** Defined terms of SLAs and roles of transition participants. Created and managed a master calendar that tracked and governed future demand. Created and managed a KPI scorecard for status and trends.

### TECHNOLOGY SERVICE DELIVERY SENIOR CONSULTANT, 1996 – 2005

Brought in for consulting role to serve as Infrastructure Service Delivery Manager supporting the bank's Investment Management (IM) and Private Banking Departments. Drove continuing improvement in the delivery and availability of critical, time sensitive technology supporting 4,000+ users, including large trading floors.

Planned and directed delivery of IT Infrastructure, Services and Support to the bank's IM and PB businesses. Guided engineers providing Server, Desktop Support, Application Services, Hardware and Help Desk Support. Managed in-house production; coordinated support and management for remote disaster recovery sites.

**Providing Strategic Leadership:** Closely liaised with business managers to set strategic and tactical business objectives. Defined and ensured compliance with SLAs for technology systems and services. Managed budgets as large as US \$5M.

### Career Notes

Early career success as a Network Engineer, successfully established metro networks among three cities for the organization. Network Administrator and Hands-on Network Manager providing guidance to 17 Network Engineers at an India-based construction company.